There are 12 of them.
12 stadiums built in the four corners of Europe.
Conceived by the most daring architects.
And built by thousands of workers and engineers.
12 gigantic arenas,
selected to host matches for a global event,
the 2020 European Football Championship.
Embarking on a unique tour of Europe,
Discovering the most beautiful stadiums on the continent.
In this episode,
the Johan Cruyff Arena in Amsterdam, Netherlands versus the Parken Stadium in Copenhagen, Denmark.
On one hand,
a stadium at a crossroads,
equipped with a smart lawn and covered with solar panels.
A global benchmark in sustainable development.
Our world is constantly changing.
We need to understand the major trends,
We need to adapt to it.
or better yet,
anticipate them.
On the other hand,
a stadium with retractable stands and roofs,
fully modular,
which also host matches,
concerts rather than office spaces.
It's great to be in this multifunctional arena.
The variety of events here,
It's really special.
It's unique.
Amsterdam and Copenhagen,
two stadiums in northern Europe.
Let's continue our journey to the North Sea coast where Amsterdam is located.
a city of over 800,000 inhabitants.
Built entirely on marshland in the 17th century,
known for its historic center and the canal district, a UNESCO World Heritage Site.
A very densely populated neighborhood,
It is impossible for architects to build a stadium in the heart of the historic center.
Attention then turned towards the southwest of the city,
in a less populated area,
next to the Pilsmerbier district.
This is where the Johan Cruyff Arena now stands.
Let's return to the name of one of the greatest players in the history of football.
Three-time Ballon d'Or winner in the 70s.
A hero for all Dutch people.
Today,
The Arena is the home of Ajax Amsterdam.
The most decorated club in the country and one of the biggest clubs in Europe with 4 Champions League titles to its credit.
Henk Markerink is the stadium manager.
Trained as an architect,
He participated in the design and selection of its location in the early 1990s.
We looked for an optimal location in terms of infrastructure.
This place is incredibly well-connected.
We are south of Amsterdam,
You could say we're really in the heart of the Netherlands,
very close to the city.
Its location is perfect.
We have the trains,
the subways,
the buses,
and even the highways that pass through here.
So it's very easy to access for cars too.
The stadium is indeed located on the A2 motorway.
A major route that crosses the entire country to transport supporters by car from major urban centers.
Maastricht,
Eindhoven or Trescht.
In 20 minutes by subway,
The stadium can be reached from the centre of Amsterdam.
And a whole network of buses makes it easy to access the arena from the surrounding suburbs.
But for the Amsterdam city council,
Building a stadium in this location was also strategic for a completely different reason.
The neighborhood was very disadvantaged,
There was a very high unemployment rate.
Together with city officials,
we said to ourselves,
if we build the stadium here,
We are going to give investment a boost.
And that will revitalize the whole neighborhood.
Today,
It's not just the stadium that has been built here.
There is a whole range of sports facilities,
leisure activities
entertainment options have skyrocketed,
like the rest of the neighborhood.
We may not have solved all the problems by building this stadium,
but the subsequent economic upturn has allowed the entire area to prosper since 1996.
In 1993,
Then began one of the biggest construction projects in the Netherlands.
Architects,
Engineers and workers will work for three years to build the largest stadium in the country.
But the first difficulties appear with the first stroke of the bulldozer.
This used to be a lake here.
so a marshy area.
The ground was very unstable.
To erect a stadium weighing tens of thousands of tons,
The architects had to draw inspiration from methods used by their ancestors to build the houses in the historic center of Amsterdam.
Houses built entirely on stilts.
The idea is then to reproduce the same principle.
To ensure the foundations,
The engineers had the holes dug in the unstable soil made of peat and clay until they reached a layer of dense sand located 16 meters deep.
In each hole,
The workers lowered huge steel structures down to the layer of sand.
Concrete was poured to fill the holes and to provide enough pillars to support the entire stadium.
In total,
The Johan Cruyff Arena rests on 2000 pillars, each 16 meters long.
45 centimeters in diameter.
With the foundations completed,
The workers were able to begin construction of the stadium, taking into account an original element from the design stage.
the presence of a road.
For architects,
A solution had to be found to fit a road in the same place.
a huge car park and a stadium.
The road was already under construction.
But it gave us an advantage.
Since there was a road,
the land was cheaper and it could be used for several things.
If we were to lift the road,
We could build a car park underneath.
At the end of the day,
We modified our plans and envisioned three buildings stacked one on top of the other.
a tunnel,
a car park and a stadium.
And that's what we built.
A first car park with 2500 spaces was therefore built.
above the foundations.
Then the road was raised to the next level.
On either side of this road,
A second level of parking has been created so that visitors can access the stands directly.
In the end,
The football pitch and the stadium rest entirely on these two levels of parking, through which the tunnel passes.
During matches,
The players move around on the pitch with cars driving just below.
By stacking the road,
the car park and the stadium,
The architects have achieved the feat of occupying the minimum amount of space in the same area to accommodate the maximum number of visitors.
1996,
The company BAM also participated in the construction of the stadium.
There are several reasons that led them to build a road under the stadium.
First of all,
The city wanted to turn this stadium into a monument.
And the best way to showcase a building,
It's about raising it up.
Afterwards,
A parking lot was needed.
If we were to raise the stadium and build a car park underneath,
This allowed two things to be built on the same ground footprint.
And then,
always to save space,
They built a road that goes through the stadium.
So,
thanks to this road,
We always had access to the area behind the stadium,
but also to all parking lots.
So I really think that's the winning combination they used to build the road and the stadium together.
The Johan Cruyff Arena is now one of those large stadiums built on the outskirts of urban areas.
London,
Glasgow,
Saint Petersburg has all established its football temple away from the city centre.
Others made a different choice.
In Copenhagen,
capital of Denmark,
Fans can travel to the match by bicycle.
Parken Stadium is located in the residential area of ​​Lostorne.
a stone's throw from the historic heart of Copenhagen.
This stadium, renovated in the 1990s, is located on the site of Copenhagen's former sports park.
over a century old.
A legendary place for all Danes.
Tom Danielson worked at the architectural firm that originally designed the renovation.
For him,
No doubt about it.
the stadium was to be rebuilt in the same location as the old one.
Various organizations have begun searching for a new location for a new national arena.
Several locations in the vicinity of Copenhagen have been studied.
It was a close call that a new national stadium wasn't built in Brombe.
But fortunately,
I would say,
And I believe that all the inhabitants of Copenhagen and all Danes would agree with me.
We finally managed to establish that it had to be here.
That's where history lies,
that is to say, at the site where the old Copenhagen athletics stadium had stood since 1912,
and where some of the very first football matches in Danish history were played.
At the turn of the 1990s,
The architects had to overcome a major challenge.
How can a new 38,000-seat stadium be built in an area that is already developed?
Before its renovation,
Parken Stadium measured approximately 100 meters by 60 meters.
The proposed new stadium has a footprint of 200 meters by 165 meters.
It is unthinkable to encroach on Fallet Parken.
It was impossible to destroy the hockey pitch, which was so precious to the Danes.
The only option,
rotate the stadium 90°.
The local football club B93 agrees to give up its training ground to accommodate the new national stadium.
The location is therefore perfectly suited.
The new footprint helps to preserve the famous residential area of ​​Pomp-le-Villiers.
Once the orientation of the new stadium has been decided,
The architects and engineers demolished almost the entire old stadium.
with the exception of the long main stand,
which then becomes a short platform.
Three new stands have been added.
Two parallel to the Astorale and a third opposite the old stand.
But the architects don't stop there.
They were taking a bold gamble for the time.
Adding offices to a stadium.
Three buildings were then constructed around the tribes.
The water stadium was built in 1992.
There were just three stands.
Since we did not own the property at the time,
We had no control.
nor on architecture,
nor on the stadium's infrastructure.
There was indeed the old main stand,
the one that had been preserved,
but it was old,
The concrete was in poor condition, as were the attached infrastructures.
clearly insufficient.
In 2009,
FC Copenhagen,
now the owner of the stadium,
they finally had the old stand dating from 1955 demolished and replaced it with a smaller stand.
At the rear of the stands,
running along the entire length of the field,
A huge office building for rent is being constructed.
This will make the stadium profitable outside of football matches.
On normal days,
when there is no match,
The stadium is still alive, though.
You meet a lot of people here.
Actually,
400 people work in our offices,
in all sorts of very different businesses.
There is a private hospital,
sports clubs,
a bodysuit...
SDS, which is a kind of therapeutic center,
all the ingredients for a business location.
We also have a 3-star restaurant in the Gile Michelin guide called Geranium.
Working here every day,
even when there is no match,
It makes him feel alive.
It gives him a unique energy.
It's a fantastic feeling.
Making a stadium profitable outside of football matches has become one of the priorities for managers.
Since its creation in 1996,
The Johan Cruyff Arena was also designed with this in mind.
It hosts numerous events throughout the year.
If we only had football,
We could not be profitable.
From the very beginning,
The stadium was designed to be multifunctional.
Ajax and the national team remain the foundation of our business.
But besides that,
There are concerts,
major events
conferences,
seminars.
The stadium is operating at full capacity.
7 days a week,
24 hours a day.
The Johan Cruyff Arena has thus become the essential concert venue for an entire country.
The world's biggest bands have performed there.
From U2 to Bon Jovi,
including the Rolling Stones.
But as the years went by,
The stadium has become a victim of its own success.
Ajax attracted huge crowds of spectators,
much more than we had anticipated.
We were also able to organize many more concerts and events than we had anticipated.
That's when we realized that our facilities were insufficient for the number of people we were receiving.
We were seriously lacking in equipment,
of restaurants,
refreshment stands,
toilets,
Short,
of a whole bunch of things.
Over the years,
The stadium is undergoing numerous renovations.
Escalators and elevators to facilitate access to the stadium.
The expansion of certain spaces.
But that's still not enough.
The stadium needs to think bigger in order to increase services and public capacity.
For architects,
This is a new challenge.
How can a stadium be significantly enlarged without drastically altering the existing structure?
The option chosen is to add a new steel structure that fits against the old stadium walls.
A kind of immense, multi-level metal cage attached to the stadium.
To support this steel structure,
New foundations are being created and the stadium's old load-bearing columns are being reinforced.
In its widest part,
The cage has two floors, each over 80 meters long.
enough to easily accommodate the 7000 supporters in the stand.
And to isolate the cage from the outside,
The architects chose a material that has already proven its worth.
We wanted to create a lot of light,
Plenty of space.
To succeed in creating such a large facade,
We chose a lightweight material in order to reduce the overall mass as much as possible.
We therefore opted for an ETFE cushion structure.
This provides transparency in certain areas.
Other parts are merely translucent.
You can still see through it.
And the enclosure is only partially insulated.
After a year and a half of work,
The east side of the stadium is finished.
But future extension work is planned on the other sides.
In a few years,
The Johan Cruyff Arena will have a much more rounded silhouette to accommodate more people and offer even more services.
Parken Stadium also began its transformation phase in the 2000s to bring new experiences to the public.
The first major change was the construction of a retractable roof.
The retractable roof was built in 2001.
simply because the Olsen brothers won Eurovision the previous year.
You should know that when your country wins Eurovision,
He welcomed him the following year.
This is a huge opportunity to welcome
30,000 people for the Eurovision final.
At the time,
only a few stadiums in the world are equipped with retractable roofs.
These are huge steel and glass panels that slide over each other to open and close.
Far too expensive for the Parken Stadium managers who ended up choosing a flexible roof supported by a series of steel frames.
Lars Ostenfeld Riemann supervised the construction of the roof.
He takes us up to a height of 35 meters.
We are here on the fixed part of the roof where we have installed this large beam along the entire length of the roof, under which is the travel rail.
This installation supports the motors but also all the inlet beams that span the entire width of the roof and allow it to be closed.
And it is precisely these engines
thanks to a system of gears that will advance and move the crossbeams.
You can see it clearly here.
The engine moves forward thanks to the rack and pinion, and once it has reached its final position,
We lower this piston and then,
We are certain that the system can no longer move.
In total,
The roof of the Stadparken is equipped with 26 motors.
each positioned at the end of the 13 steel beams that span the stadium.
26 motors that must move at a constant speed,
guided by rails.
If one engine runs faster than another,
one of the steel beams may suddenly become deflected.
This is a huge risk because not only are the beams no longer parallel,
but this also generates a lot of force and movement within the system.
which is very bad for the entire structure.
To avoid disaster,
Each motor and each beam is equipped with sensors that measure their movements in real time.
Two people on each side of the roof monitor the smooth progress of the process.
At the slightest problem,
They can stop the roof's movement.
But before proceeding to close the roof,
The technicians must perform another maneuver.
Because supporting a roof weighing several hundred tons was not planned for the old stadium structure.
Installing a roof over the existing structure was really very difficult.
The original roof already housed some of the grandstand seating.
but these structures could not support an entire new roof.
So we were forced to reinforce the existing roof in many places.
The engineers therefore had to think of a way to reinforce the two enormous steel side beams.
They designed two pivoting columns in the center of each one.
When the stadium is open-air,
The columns are folded and suspended under the existing roof.
Before the roof is closed,
The first thing to do is to rotate the columns and fix them securely to the ground.
When
Everything is in place.
The roof can begin to close.
In order to minimize the load on the stands,
the 13 beams of the...
The roofs are connected to each other by PVC membranes.
These membranes,
made up of several layers,
are successively inflated with pressurized air,
in order to stiffen the entire roof structure.
To fold down the roof,
The air pumps are switched off.
The membranes deflate,
The beams are placed close together.
The PVC membranes hang like curtains between each beam.
The assembly will then slide under the rigid roof of stand D.
Grace
with a retractable roof...
Parken Stadium has been able to host the biggest sporting and musical events in the country.
A few years ago,
The band Coldplay used to perform here.
One hour before the doors open,
when the musicians were doing their soundcheck and the spectators were queuing outside,
Chris Martin,
the band's singer,
came to see us at the office and told us
"I can't play in the rain."
It's too difficult for me and it's a real shame for the audience.
It's going to ruin the whole atmosphere of the concert.
Can you close the roof?
Everyone remained silent.
No one wanted to answer that question.
In barely an hour,
This meant bringing in the technicians,
to install everything and then deploy the roof.
That's a sign...
Life has turned everything upside down, actually.
Eventually,
We quickly organized a production meeting and everyone said,
Let's do it.
Let's deploy the roof.
We postponed the concert by one hour.
But Coldplay was able to play.
Chris Martin was delighted.
We all received a badge that said "Love".
on top and everyone was very happy.
Parken Stadium also has a major advantage in hosting concerts and shows within its grounds.
a retractable grandstand.
80 meters long,
It was the largest mobile grandstand in all of Scandinavia at the time of its construction.
Michael Jensen is the stadium's technical director.
With each manipulation,
He is there to oversee the smooth running of operations.
When the new grandstand was built,
We needed space downstairs to build the stage when there are concerts.
Before,
We had a mobile scaffold on which we placed seats,
and it took about a week to assemble.
and it also took a week to dismantle afterwards.
So that's why we had a mobile grandstand built.
to be able to switch quickly between concerts and football matches.
40 minutes,
Michael and his colleagues can fit in the 3900 seats supported by the steel structures of the grandstand.
The bleachers move thanks to an ingenious system devised by the injectors.
Each row of seats is supported by a steel structure.
These structures are built in such a way as to fit together according to a collision system.
The entire stand is divided into 8 sections.
Each section is set in motion by means of a motor.
Once activated,
Each motor winds a steel chain which pulls the lower row of the grandstand.
The movement of the lower row then in turn affects all the seats above it.
The structures beneath the stands then fit together, one under the other.
freeing up space in front of the stands.
With each movement from the stands,
Michael and his colleagues systematically monitor what is happening under the stands.
A few of us go underneath to take care of the various security procedures.
because it is deployed in three stages.
And at each stage,
We check if everything is in place and properly aligned.
We mustn't let things go off the rails.
It would be catastrophic if it moved at an angle.
because it would be very difficult to put it back straight.
So that,
This is a procedure that requires a lot of attention from us.
Once stacked,
The 19 rows of seats form a wall more than 6 meters high.
The space freed up allows for the installation of the stage for the artists.
And for easy access to behind-the-scenes areas,
the stand needs to undergo a second transformation.
The mobile grandstand we have here gives us the advantage of being able to move the middle section out when we have concerts.
And that gives us enormous advantages.
Because when you remove the middle section and build the scene in front,
We can bring all the equipment directly onto the stage.
To create this hole in the mobile grandstand,
Mickaël and his team have to remove more than 150 seats at a time.
that is the equivalent of 5 tonnes to be moved by forklift.
Seats are also being removed from each stand to create access routes and emergency exits.
Two exits from stand C,
two others in stand B and one exit in stand A.
In the end,
Parken Stadium is transformed into a huge arena ready to welcome the public for major events.
And to improve the acoustics during concerts,
Huge woolen drapes are unfurled under the roof and along the buildings surrounding the stage.
During the concerts,
Curtains are always installed on office towers because they are made of glass and sound reverberates off the glass.
It creates an echo and gives us very bad acoustics.
With these thick LED curtains,
the sound is immediately muffled.
This makes the acoustics of the stadium excellent.
At each concert,
Thousands of fans gather on the football pitch.
Enough to destroy the lawn in a few hours.
To avoid damaging the grass,
Mickaël and his teams use very efficient equipment.
To protect the lawn,
which is our sacred ground here in the stadium,
These large panels are installed on top of the grass.
This will become the floor to accommodate all the audience members who come to see the concert and remain standing.
The plates are very thick.
They protect the lawn from trampling.
but there are also holes to allow air to circulate and the grass to breathe.
On the surface of each panel,
Dozens of aligned holes were drilled to allow air to circulate at grass level.
Spilled liquids do not pass through the holes.
They are collected in channels carved into the panel.
On the underside of the panel in contact with the lawn,
Circular feet slightly raise the panel,
which allows for a better distribution of the workload.
Each one square meter panel weighs 12 kilos and is easily handled by two people.
However, six hours are needed to completely cover the stadium's lawn by heart.
If these panels protect the grass from public trampling,
They were also designed to allow grass to grow even once covered.
The 60 mm thick panel has cavities on its underside that allow air to circulate and provide enough space for grass to grow.
The material,
high-density polyethylene plastic,
is naturally translucent.
It therefore allows light to pass through and does not stop the process of photosynthesis.
The solar radiation that passes through the panel removes the water contained in the soil.
A cloud of vapor then forms under each cavity.
The moisture eventually condenses under the droplet, and drops then fall onto the grass.
providing the water necessary for its survival.
Therefore, the lawn does not need to be watered when it is covered by the panels.
We can host concerts that are organized very quickly.
with very quick installation and uninstallation.
The panels covering the lawn were removed, and a few hours later,
There's a football match taking place here.
But the panels cannot be left on the grass for more than 72 consecutive hours.
no more than 3 days.
Otherwise,
The grass will rise with air.
water, and especially water.
of light.
It may turn yellow.
to brown,
to lose its beautiful green color.
Playing a football match after a concert is therefore not always the ideal solution for keeping a pitch in perfect condition.
Amsterdam,
The managers of the Johan Cruyff Arena made a completely different choice.
They opted for a complete change of the turf after the concert season.
Under normal circumstances,
We have a season of festivals and concerts.
It starts at the end of the league matches,
So around mid-May,
And it ends in May.
That represents two and a half months.
almost three months for the concerts.
That's far too long a period for a covered lawn.
SO,
at the beginning of the concert season,
We are installing an aluminium floor over the grass.
So,
the trucks,
Cranes or trolleys can move freely to set up the concerts.
Actually,
We let the lawn die.
But at the end of the concert season,
The floor is removed and a brand new one is installed.
While the Dutch are world-renowned for their vast tulip fields,
They also have a perfect command of turf cultivation.
We are in Eithwiesen.
140 km from the Johan Cruyff Arena.
This is where the future pitch of the stadium is being prepared.
A lawn of a rather unusual kind.
A hybrid lawn.
Yves Decocker is the sales director for this lawn reinforced with a synthetic membrane.
This synthetic fabric,
this membrane,
We are going to inject artificial fibers.
Then we cover everything with custom-made sand.
of a very specific particle size.
It should not be too thick,
not too crude,
Not too thin either.
It has to be absolutely perfect.
And on top of these 30 mm of sand,
we sow the grass.
The hybrid lawn consists of a layer of polypropylene plastic fabric,
onto which 6 cm long artificial polyethylene fibers are injected,
in order to strengthen the structure.
These fibers are fixed by a polyurethane spray which waterproofs the carpet and makes it insensitive to climate change.
A 4cm layer of sand is placed on top of the synthetic fibers.
From this specific sand and the sown seeds,
The grass develops strong roots that will grow into the sand and become entangled in the carpet.
After 3 to 4 months,
when the natural grass is sufficiently dense and reaches a little over 2 cm in thickness above the sand,
The turf is then ready to be delivered.
But how to collect the sample?
transporting and installing an entire lawn in just a few hours?
The solution was conceived in 1997.
one year after the stadium opened.
We used all our creativity and invented our own technique for regrowing grass.
These are rolls of turf, 5 cm thick.
one meter wide and 8 meters long,
large rolls.
He pissed me off.
develop a specific cutting machine,
work with farmers to cultivate these patches properly.
This was our first innovation,
Rolled turf to replace the field in record time.
Today,
This technique has proven itself and is used in many parliamentary stadiums.
No fewer than 25 trucks are needed to transport more than 300 rolls of vibrated air.
50 people will work tirelessly to prepare and level the ground before covering the 7500 m² of the stadium with these large plots of grass.
A veritable giant patchwork
where the grass panels are directly opposite each other,
no glue or sewing required.
The weight of the panels is sufficient to hold them in place.
Only 14 hours will have passed between the delivery of the rolls and the handover of a brand new pitch,
ready to host the next match.
Hybrid turf raises many questions.
A hybrid lawn,
Does that mean we're playing on artificial turf?
No.
And I want to be very clear on this point.
Playing on a hybrid grass surface,
It's like playing on natural grass.
The trick,
This is because synthetic fabrics and fibers are actually always below the level of natural grass.
So,
even when you play on it or touch it,
you will be in contact with natural grass.
The synthetic part of it is always located under the mowing surface.
So you're playing on real grass.
You will have natural playing conditions.
It's natural grass reinforced with synthetic fibers that you can't see or feel.
Thanks to the reinforced turf,
The pitch can last a whole football season without suffering serious damage.
But natural grass,
She,
needs regular care.
Again,
The stadium managers have innovated and proposed a system capable of monitoring the health of the pitch in real time.
The grass is the most sensitive element of our stadium,
because we want to offer Ajax players the very best in terms of pitch.
For that,
We have equipped ourselves with a system that allows us to control the quality of the ground.
It notably consists of 15 sensors placed under the turf,
distributed across the entire surface of the lawn and which constantly measure the temperature,
humidity and the amount of light received by the grass.
We also have a sensor installed behind the lawnmowers.
These devices record data at the time of mowing that measures the vitality and density of the grass.
This information allows us to know precisely the condition of the lawn.
Is she doing well?
Is she in good health?
Or does it have deficiencies in fertilizer or light?
With a 3.0 lawn,
The teams in charge of maintenance have a wealth of data that helps them make the right decisions.
can know precisely when and where more water or more light is needed to accelerate air regrowth.
The data collected also allows us to anticipate the future.
At the strategic level,
We can say that if it's too matte,
We can predict how long the grass will need to rest.
So,
Maintenance operations are necessary.
This allows us to anticipate how the quality of the lawn will change over time.
This allows us to better organize our interventions.
And it also allows Ajax players to know how the matches have damaged the pitch and what conditions they will be playing in during the next matches.
From the 2010s onwards,
The leaders have set themselves another challenge.
To make the Johan Cruyff Arena a showcase for sustainable development.
The engineers had to revise their design in order to improve energy consumption.
The goal?
Use less fossil fuel in favor of more modern and sustainable sources.
7000 m² of panels are...
Solar panels were thus installed all around the roof,
the equivalent of the surface area of ​​a fleet's field.
We produce 10%
of our energy thanks to our solar panels.
The other 90%
come from wind turbines located about 30 km from here.
30 km from here.
Thanks to all of this,
We therefore use entirely green electricity to be able to manage all of our facilities.
It turned out that these solar panels were generating far more energy than needed.
But alas,
in times when we didn't need it.
The sun shines during the day,
while the matches and events take place in the evening.
So we thought...
Something is missing from our system.
We need to be able to store solar energy.
After two years of development,
in partnership with a car manufacturer,
The solution has finally been found.
The surplus electricity will be stored in car batteries.
The Arena's storage room is currently equipped with 148 new batteries or batteries from used vehicles.
These batteries are connected to the electricity grid via 4 bidirectional converters.
When they are powered and charged at
100%, the batteries can store up to 3 MW of electricity.
Enough to provide sufficient energy during matches or in case of a power outage.
Aside from competitions and concerts,
The energy stored in the batteries is also used to power the public grid during peak consumption periods.
The electricity is then redistributed via the converter which transforms the direct current coming out of the batteries into alternating current used on the public electricity grid.
The storage room is monitored 24 hours a day.
In case of overheating,
The team is ready to intervene.
It is also necessary to ensure that the electricity supplied by the stadium complies with the public network distribution standards.
What you see here,
This is the bandwidth on which we agreed on the frequency with the network operator.
Actually,
The battery ensures that this frequency remains within the bandwidth.
So if demand and usage vary greatly,
The battery ensures it stays within this bandwidth.
that is to say, within the 50 Hz range.
Engineers have also found other alternative energy sources.
So,
The changing rooms and offices are now cooled by drawing cold water from the bottom of a lake located near the stadium.
The warm water is then discharged back into the lake.
The stadium escalators,
coupled to a dynamo,
produce electricity which is in turn sent to the grid.
Thanks to these technologies distributed throughout the stadium,
The Johan Cruyff Arena managed to achieve a zero carbon footprint as early as 2015.
This makes it one of the most modern stadiums in the world today.
People from all over the world came to admire what is now called the fifth generation of the football stadium.
We are pioneers in this technology.
And when they asked UEFA or FIFA where to find inspiration,
they replied
"Go to Amsterdam,
"This is the stadium of the future."
For his part,
Parken Stadium proves to the world that such a venue can diversify.
At the same time,
This offers a significant advantage.
That's because there's life in the stadium practically at all hours of the day and every day of the week.
It does not remain unused like many stadiums that only experience a peak in activity.
once a week when there is a football match,
or only a few times a week.
We wanted it to be a living, breathing house.
a house that offers services to city dwellers in this neighborhood,
here in Osterau,
in Copenhagen and throughout Denmark.
Two stadiums with different architecture.
But two stadiums that have managed to preserve the spirit of sport while offering the public new experiences.
Football temples transformed into veritable arenas where services,
innovation,
hospitality,
Quality has become the new value.
The values ​​of these 21st-century cathedrals.